New York State Bureau of Industrial and Technical Education Records 5377
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State Bureau of Industrial and Technical Education Records
1940-1977
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State Bureau of Industrial and Technical Education
5377
5.5 cubic feet
5.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Monographs in the fundamentals of machine shop practice, sheet metal work, etc., prepared for the public vocational schools of New York State to assist them in pre-employment and supplementary training and supplementary training.
5620264
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 15, 2005
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 11, 2019
Biographical / Historical
To meet the need for appropriate instructional material for workers entering war industries at the start of World War II, the New York State Education Department, through the Bureau of Industrial and Technical Education, organized curriculum laboratories at Cornell University, New York City, Buffalo, Rochester and Syracuse. The curriculum laboratories prepared monographs in the fundamentals of machine shop practice, sheet metal work, etc., for the public vocational schools of New York State to assist them in pre-employment training and also supplementary training for up-grading employed people.
The Curriculum Construction laboratory at Cornell was supervised by Professor Lynn A. Emerson of the College of Engineering, who also acted as a consultant to the other laboratories. Copies of the manuals were distributed to national defense training centers throughout the United States.
Scope and Contents
Monographs in the fundamentals of machine shop practice, sheet metal work, etc., prepared for the public vocational schools of New York State to assist them in pre-employment and supplementary training and supplementary training.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Technical education; New York (State) Bureau of Industrial and Technical Education
5620264
- Advanced Blue Print Reading for Machine Trades, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Vol I.
- Advanced Blue Print Reading for Machine Trades, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Vol II
- Alternating Current Fundamentals, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Alternating Current Fundamentals - Radio, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Assembly for Beginners in Aircraft Metal Work, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Part I Sub, Line & Final Assembly
- Assembly for Beginners in Aircraft Metal Work, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Part II Sub, Line & Final Assembly
- Baking for The United State Merchant Marine, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bench Work for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Blue Print Reading for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bus and Truck Driving Training, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Concrete Form Construction for Beginners in Carpentry, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Course of Study in Stewardships for United State Merchant Marine, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Course Outline and Instructional Material in Cooking Prepared for the United States Merchant Marine, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Course Outline - Radio Service and Repair (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Direct - Current Fundamentals, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Drill Press Work, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Electric Motor Control, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Electrical Circuit Diagrams, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Electrical Measurements, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Electronics, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Fabrication for Beginners in Aircraft Metal Work, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Factory Production Methods Applied to Aircraft Teaching, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Farm Machinery Maintenance, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Farm Tractor Maintenance, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Framing, Sheathing and Insulation for Beginners in Carpentry, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Fundamentals of Pressure and Temperature Instruments, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Fundamentals of Radio Receivers, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- General Repair Tools for Beginners in Automobile Mechanics, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Glider Ground Trainer Construction, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Heat Treatment of Metals for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Improving Instruction Through Supervision, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Industrial Electronics, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Inspection Practice - Aircraft Manufacture - Unit A (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Inspection Practice - Aircraft Manufacture - Unit B (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Inspection Practice - Aircraft Manufacture - Unit C (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Inspection Practice for Aircraft Manufacture - Unit A B C, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Inspection Practice - Machined Parts, Tools & Gages - Unit A, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Inspection Practice - Machined Parts, Tools & Gages - Unit B, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Inspection Practice - Machined Parts, Tools and Gages - Unit C, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Inspection Practice - Units ABC, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- The Instructor and His Job, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Interior and Exterior Trim for Beginners in Carpentry, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Job Sheet Units for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Junior Aviation Maintenance and Repair Course, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Lathe Work for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Light Assembly Practice - Radio, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Light Machine Operation - Lathe Work, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Light Machine Operation (Supplement No. One), 1942 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Locomotive Firing, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Mathematics for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Measurement for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Metal Working Industry - Part I, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Methods of Teaching Shop work, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Milling Machine Work for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Precision Measurement, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- The Preparation of Meat for the United States Merchant Marine, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Riveting for Beginners in Aircraft Metal Work, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Sawmill Operation & Management, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Scale Model Aircraft Project, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Shaper Work for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Sheet Metal Work - Hand Process - Part I, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Sheet Metal Work - Job Sheet Series - Part I, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Sheet Metal Work - Machine Processes - Part I, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Sheet Metal Work - Measurement and Layout - Part I, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Sheet Metal Work - Teachers Manual - Part I, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Shop Arithmetic, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Shop Talks on Inspection Practice Machined Parts, Tools & Gages - Aircraft Manufacture, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Suggested Teacher's Outline for the Training of Women in Ordinance Inspection, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Suggested Tests Tor the Student in Light Machine Operation, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Teachers Manual and Answer Book for Suggested Unit Course in Blue Print Reading for Beginners in Machine Shop Practice, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Teachers Manual and Answer Book for the Suggested Course in Advanced Blue Print Reading for Machine Trades, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Vol. I and II
- Teaching Materials for Industrial Education, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Unit Course in Assembly-for Beginners in Aviation Mechanics, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Unit Course in Riveting for Beginners in Aviation Mechanics, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- The Use of Hand Tools and Portable Machinery for Beginners in Carpentry, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- War Industries Training Program - Practical Teaching (Box 4, Folder 12)